<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/FNS-Spurgeon/4-TEI-Encoding/refs/heads/main/odd/tei_chaucerAllusions.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="part3_p85_a2">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>1866, Unknown. Chaucer—His Position, Life, and Influence.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="DS">Devani Singh</name>
          <resp>Principal investigator of the project. Supervision of the workflow and control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="EL">Elina Leblanc</name>
          <resp>Data modelling, OCR correction, text encoding and uploading in the database.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="JS">Jordan Skinner</name>
          <resp>Corpus enhacement and verification of data accuracy. Control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Project SNSF "Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities" (n°225925)</publisher>
        <authority>Department of English Language and Literature, Faculty of Humanities, University of Geneva</authority>
        <address>
          <addrLine>12, boulevard des Philosophes</addrLine>
          <addrLine>1205 Genève</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY</licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>Unknown</author>
            <date cert="high" when="1866">1866</date>
            <title level="a">Chaucer—His Position, Life, and Influence.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion</title>
            <author>Spurgeon, Caroline</author>
            <note>We used the digitizations made by Google for the University of Michigan (Public Domain, Google-Digitized). The facsimile can be found on HathiTrust.<ptr target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015066185086"/></note>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
              <publisher>University Press</publisher>
              <date>1925</date>
            </imprint>
            <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="part">III</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page" source="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015066185086?urlappend=%3Bseq=403">85</biblScope>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The digital part of the SNSF project 'Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities' aims to create the first open-access database dedicated to the criticism and reception of Chaucer throughout history. It draws on the compilation and cataloguing work carried out by Professor Caroline Spurgeon (1869–1942) and collected in 'Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion'. This work consists of three volumes and a supplement, which will be systematically transcribed, corrected, enriched, encoded and published online, in order to facilitate future research and bring new perspectives to light.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>The original spelling and punctuation are retained. Meaningful layouts are reproduced, i.e. verses, printed marginalia, dots lines, tables, etc. However, we do not consider, the line breaks for prose, the columns or the curly brackets. The same rules apply for special characters and glyphs. Otiose letters are normalised, as well as spaces before punctuation marks.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="FoNDUE" version="0.1">
          <label>FoNDUE</label>
          <ptr target="https://fondue.unige.ch/"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#biography" target="#english"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2026-06-15" who="#EL">Creation of the TEI file and enrichment of data</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="allusion">
        <milestone unit="page" n="85"/>
        
        <ab type="imprint">1866. Unknown. <hi rend="italic">Chaucer—His Position, Life, and Influence</hi>, [in] The Westminster Review, July, 1866, vol. xxx, pp. 184-200.</ab>
        
        <ab type="quotation">
          <seg type="editorial">[A long and appreciative article of a general nature, with
            a good deal about Chaucer’s life and times, and something
            on his language, and on the text of the <hi rend="italic">Canterbury Tales</hi> in
            recent editions.]</seg>
            
          <seg><note place="margin">[p.184]</note> Chaucer . . . may be read with comparative ease. There
            are a few of his phrases obscure; a few of his endings silent;
            a few of his words obsolete. But we require neither grammar
            nor glossary to understand and enjoy him.</seg>
            
          <seg><note place="margin">[p. 199]</note> Not much has yet been done to make Chaucer's works
            more popular or more intelligible. <add>[There are great difficulties,
            his text is uncertain, often obscure. Tyrwhitt has done a
            great deal to remove obscurities, though he]</add> often unnecessarily
            and pretentiously displays his abstruse and curious learning.</seg>
            
          <seg type="editorial">[But in spite of his pedantry, Tyrwhitt’s text of the C. Tales
            in 1755 [sic], seems as good as that of Wright, in 1847.
            The worst features of Tyrwhitt’s edn. reappear in that of
            Routledge [1863], where "none of Tyrwhitt’s mistakes are
            corrected nor his defects supplied." Robert Bell’s edn.
            1854, is the best, by this editor nearly everything which
            can explain or illustrate his author has been skilfully condensed.]</seg>
            
          <seg>But it is not likely that all Chaucer's writings—
            consisting, as they mostly do, of translations,—can ever
            become popular. We still require an edition ot the
            "Canterbury Tales" in which the obsolete words, opinions and
            customs will be explained, and the obsolete pronunciation
            indicated.</seg>
        </ab>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>