<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/FNS-Spurgeon/4-TEI-Encoding/refs/heads/main/odd/tei_chaucerAllusions.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="part3_p78_a2">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>1865, Frederick Denison Maurice. On Books.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="DS">Devani Singh</name>
          <resp>Principal investigator of the project. Supervision of the workflow and control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="EL">Elina Leblanc</name>
          <resp>Data modelling, OCR correction, text encoding and uploading in the database.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="JS">Jordan Skinner</name>
          <resp>Corpus enhacement and verification of data accuracy. Control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Project SNSF "Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities" (n°225925)</publisher>
        <authority>Department of English Language and Literature, Faculty of Humanities, University of Geneva</authority>
        <address>
          <addrLine>12, boulevard des Philosophes</addrLine>
          <addrLine>1205 Genève</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY</licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author cert="high" role="M" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/37075904">Maurice, Frederick Denison</author>
            <date cert="high" when="1865">1865</date>
            <title level="a">On Books.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion</title>
            <author>Spurgeon, Caroline</author>
            <note>We used the digitizations made by Google for the University of Michigan (Public Domain, Google-Digitized). The facsimile can be found on HathiTrust.<ptr target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015066185086"/></note>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
              <publisher>University Press</publisher>
              <date>1925</date>
            </imprint>
            <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="part">III</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page">78-79</biblScope>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The digital part of the SNSF project 'Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities' aims to create the first open-access database dedicated to the criticism and reception of Chaucer throughout history. It draws on the compilation and cataloguing work carried out by Professor Caroline Spurgeon (1869–1942) and collected in 'Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion'. This work consists of three volumes and a supplement, which will be systematically transcribed, corrected, enriched, encoded and published online, in order to facilitate future research and bring new perspectives to light.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>The original spelling and punctuation are retained. Meaningful layouts are reproduced, i.e. verses, printed marginalia, dots lines, tables, etc. However, we do not consider, the line breaks for prose, the columns or the curly brackets. The same rules apply for special characters and glyphs. Otiose letters are normalised, as well as spaces before punctuation marks.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="FoNDUE" version="0.1">
          <label>FoNDUE</label>
          <ptr target="https://fondue.unige.ch/"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#criticism" target="#general"/>
        <catRef scheme="#works" target="#criticism"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2026-06-15" who="#EL">Creation of the TEI file and enrichment of data</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="allusion">
        <milestone unit="page" n="78"/>
        
        <ab type="imprint">1865. Maurice, Frederick Denison. <hi rend="italic">On Books</hi>, [a lecture delivered Nov. 1865, printed in] The Friendship of Books and other Lectures, 1874, pp. 76-7.</ab>
        
        <ab type="quotation">
          <seg><note place="margin">[pp. 76-7]</note> Chaucer was possibly the friend of Wycliffe—certainly
            shared many of his sympathies and antipathies. He loved
            the priest, or, as he was called, the secular priest, who went
            among the people, and cared for them as his fellow-country-
            men; he intensely disliked the friars, who flattered them and
            cursed them, and in both ways governed them and degraded
            them. His education had been different from Wycliffe's, his
            early poetical powers had been called forth by the ladies and
            gentlemen of the court. He mingled much French with his
            speech, as they did; he acquired from them a kind of
            acquaintance with life which Wycliffe could not obtain in
            the Oxford schools. Had he remained under their influence
            he might have been merely a very musical court singer; but
            he entered into fellowship with common citizens. He became
            a keen observer of all the different forms of life and society
            in his time—a keen observer, and, as all such are, genial,
            friendly, humorous, able to understand men about him by
            sympathising with them, able to understand the stories of the
            past by his experience of the present. Without being a
            reformer like Wycliffe, he helped forward the Reformation
            by making men acquainted with themselves and their fellows,
            by stripping off disguises, and by teaching them to open
            their eyes to the beautiful world which lay about them.
            Chaucer is the genuine specimen of an English poet—a type
            of the best who were to come after him; with cordial affection
            for men and for nature; often tempted to coarseness, often
            yielding to his baser nature in his desire to enter into all the
            
            <milestone unit="page" n="79"/>
            
            different experiences of men; apt through this desire, and
            through his hatred of what was insincere, to say many things
            of which he had need to repent, and of which he did repent;
            but never losing his loyalty to what was pure, his reverence
            for what was divine. . . . The English books which live
            through ages are those which connect themselves with human
            life and action. His other poems, though graceful and
            harmonious, are only remembered, because in his "Canterbury
            Tales" he has come directly into contact with the
            hearts and thoughts, the sufferings and sins, of men and
            women, and has given the clearest pictures we possess of all
            the distinctions and occupations in his own day.</seg>
        </ab>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
