<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/FNS-Spurgeon/4-TEI-Encoding/refs/heads/main/odd/tei_chaucerAllusions.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="part5_p141_a2">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>1845, J. Meyer. [Article Chaucer in] Das grosse Conversations-Lexicon.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="DS">Devani Singh</name>
          <resp>Principal investigator of the project. Supervision of the workflow and control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="EL">Elina Leblanc</name>
          <resp>Data modelling, OCR correction, text encoding and uploading in the database.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="JS">Jordan Skinner</name>
          <resp>Corpus enhacement and verification of data accuracy. Control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Project SNSF "Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities" (n°225925)</publisher>
        <authority>Department of English Language and Literature, Faculty of Humanities, University of Geneva</authority>
        <address>
          <addrLine>12, boulevard des Philosophes</addrLine>
          <addrLine>1205 Genève</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY</licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author cert="high" role="M">Meyer, J.</author>
            <date cert="high" when="1845">1845</date>
            <title level="a">[Article Chaucer in] Das grosse Conversations-Lexicon.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion</title>
            <author>Spurgeon, Caroline</author>
            <note>We used the digitizations made by Google for the University of Michigan (Public Domain, Google-Digitized). The facsimile can be found on HathiTrust.<ptr target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015066184931"/></note>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
              <publisher>University Press</publisher>
              <date>1925</date>
            </imprint>
            <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="part">V</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page">141-142</biblScope>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The digital part of the SNSF project 'Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities' aims to create the first open-access database dedicated to the criticism and reception of Chaucer throughout history. It draws on the compilation and cataloguing work carried out by Professor Caroline Spurgeon (1869–1942) and collected in 'Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion'. This work consists of three volumes and a supplement, which will be systematically transcribed, corrected, enriched, encoded and published online, in order to facilitate future research and bring new perspectives to light.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>The original spelling and punctuation are retained. Meaningful layouts are reproduced, i.e. verses, printed marginalia, dots lines, tables, etc. However, we do not consider, the line breaks for prose, the columns or the curly brackets. The same rules apply for special characters and glyphs. Otiose letters are normalised, as well as spaces before punctuation marks.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="FoNDUE" version="0.1">
          <label>FoNDUE</label>
          <ptr target="https://fondue.unige.ch/"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="de">German</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#biography" target="#german"/>
        <catRef scheme="#works" target="#criticism"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2026-07-13" who="#EL">Creation of the TEI file and enrichment of data</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="allusion">
        <milestone unit="page" n="141"/>
        
        <ab type="imprint">1845. Meyer, J. [Article <hi rend="italic">Chaucer</hi> in] <hi rend="italic">Das grosse Conversations-Lexicon</hi> für die gebildeten Stände. Hildburghausen, 1840-55, vol. vii, pt. ii, 1845, pp. 47-49.</ab>
        
        <ab type="quotation">
          <seg><note place="margin">[p. 47, col. 2]</note>Chaucer, Geoffroy, der Vater der englischen Dichtkunst
            genannt. Wie eifrig bes. engl. Biographen über C.'s Lebensumstände
            auch nachgeforscht haben, so ist doch bis jetzt
            noch Vieles dunkel geblieben. Das J. 1328 wird gewöhul.
            als das seiner Geburt bezeichnet <add>[etc., a full life, based
            on Leland, Godwin, the Testament of Love, etc.]</add>.</seg>
            
          <seg><note place="margin">[p. 48, col. 2]</note>C.'s Werke sind in verschiedenen Handschriften
            aufbewahrt, was ihre fortwährende Popularität bezeugt, und
            nachher häufig gedruckt worden. Eines der ersten Produkte von
            Caxtons Presse ist eine Ausgabe der Canterbury-Erzählungen. . . .
            Als Beweis von C.'s Popularität in Schottland
            mag gelten, dass eine der frühesten Arbeiten der schottischen
            Presse seine “Klage des schwarzen Ritters" war, die 1508
            von Chapman und Myllar . . . gedruckt wurde. <add>[Thynne’s
            1532 edn., noted and Tyrwhitt's edn. of the C. Tales much
            praised, “ein Muster der Akkuratesse und kritischen
            Behandlung."]</add></seg>
            
          <seg><note place="margin">[p. 49, col.1]</note>C.'s Verdienste als Dichter sind nicht gewöhnlicher Art,
            aber indem wir sie zu würdigen suchen, müssen wir das
            Zeitalter betrachten, in welchem er lebte und dichtete. C.
            musste die Sprache erst schaffen, in der er schrieb; auch in
            England herrschte die Unsitte, dass man am liebsten in
            fremden Zungen sprach und darüber die eigene Muttersprache
            vernachlässigte . . . <add>[an account of earlier English
            14th century poetry, Piers Plowman, Gower.]</add> C. mag schon
            als Dichter bekannt gewesen seyn, als Langland seine
            Visionen schrieb, sein grösstes Werk fällt aber zwanzig Jahre
            später.</seg>
            
          <seg>Sein Hauptverdienst in Bezug auf die Versifikation
            besteht darin, dass er sie natürlicher, regelmässiger und
            gedrängter machte, indem er die Alliteration abschaffte
            und den unregelmässigen Alexandriner in eine
            
            <milestone unit="page" n="142"/>
            
            Kunstgerechtere Form brachte. Sein Versmass, die zehn-und-
            achtsylbige Zeile, ist fast von allen englischen Dichtern, von
            Spencer bis Byron, beibehalten worden.</seg>
            
          <seg>In C.'s Schriften fühlt man nicht nur seinen eigenen
            persönlichen Charakter und Geist, sondern auch den
            Einfluss seines Verkehrs mit der Welt. <add>[His followers
            imitated his style and manner, but were quite unable to
            catch his spirit and character. It is noteworthy that C.
            translated many French and Italian works into English, but
            always in such a way that they had far more the character
            of original works than of translations.]</add> Lebhafte Phantasie,
            Eleganz und Schönheit der Beschreibungen bezeichnen alle
            seine Werke; aber all die Anmuth und Schönheit seiner
            allegor. Schriften bleibt weit hinter seinem Talent zurück,
            das Leben der Menschen zu schildern, wie er es in den
            unsterblichen Canterbury-Erzählungen that. In diesem
            Werke . . . bringt er einen bunten Haufen allerhand
            "sündhaften Volkes" zusammen . . . <add>[description of the O.
            Tales.]</add></seg>
            
          <seg><note place="margin">[p. 49, col. 2]</note>Nichts übertrifft die Kunst, mit welcher die Lebensart
            u. die Eigenthümlichkeiten der Pilger in der Haupteinleitung
            geschildert sind. Jede einzelne Erzählung ist ein wahrer
            Schatz von Humor und ein Zeugniss genauester Kenntniss
            der menschlichen Natur; dieses Werk C.’s bleibt stets eine
            der schönsten Zierden der engl. Literatur.</seg>
        </ab>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>