<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/FNS-Spurgeon/4-TEI-Encoding/refs/heads/main/odd/tei_chaucerAllusions.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="part3_p136_a1">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>1884, Algernon Charles Swinburne. A Midsummer Holiday.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="DS">Devani Singh</name>
          <resp>Principal investigator of the project. Supervision of the workflow and control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="EL">Elina Leblanc</name>
          <resp>Data modelling, OCR correction, text encoding and uploading in the database.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="JS">Jordan Skinner</name>
          <resp>Corpus enhacement and verification of data accuracy. Control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Project SNSF "Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities" (n°225925)</publisher>
        <authority>Department of English Language and Literature, Faculty of Humanities, University of Geneva</authority>
        <address>
          <addrLine>12, boulevard des Philosophes</addrLine>
          <addrLine>1205 Genève</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY</licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author cert="high" role="M" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/41846937">Swinburne, Algernon Charles</author>
            <date cert="high" when="1884">1884</date>
            <title level="a">A Midsummer Holiday.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion</title>
            <author>Spurgeon, Caroline</author>
            <note>We used the digitizations made by Google for the University of Michigan (Public Domain, Google-Digitized). The facsimile can be found on HathiTrust.<ptr target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015066185086"/></note>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
              <publisher>University Press</publisher>
              <date>1925</date>
            </imprint>
            <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="part">III</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page" source="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015066185086?urlappend=%3Bseq=462">136</biblScope>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The digital part of the SNSF project 'Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities' aims to create the first open-access database dedicated to the criticism and reception of Chaucer throughout history. It draws on the compilation and cataloguing work carried out by Professor Caroline Spurgeon (1869–1942) and collected in 'Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion'. This work consists of three volumes and a supplement, which will be systematically transcribed, corrected, enriched, encoded and published online, in order to facilitate future research and bring new perspectives to light.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>The original spelling and punctuation are retained. Meaningful layouts are reproduced, i.e. verses, printed marginalia, dots lines, tables, etc. However, we do not consider, the line breaks for prose, the columns or the curly brackets. The same rules apply for special characters and glyphs. Otiose letters are normalised, as well as spaces before punctuation marks.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="FoNDUE" version="0.1">
          <label>FoNDUE</label>
          <ptr target="https://fondue.unige.ch/"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass/>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2026-05-21" who="#EL">Creation of the TEI file and enrichment of data</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="allusion">
        <milestone unit="page" n="136"/>
        
        <ab type="imprint">1884. Swinburne, Algernon Charles. <hi rend="italic">A Midsummer Holiday</hi>, iii, <hi rend="italic">On a Country Road</hi>, pp. 9-11. (Poems, 1904, 6 vols., vol. vi, pp. 9-10.)</ab>
        
        <ab type="quotation">
          <seg>
            <lg>
              <note place="margin">[p. 9]</note> <l>Along these low pleached lanes, on such a day,</l>
              <l>So soft a day as this, through shade and sun,</l>
              <l>With glad grave eyes that scanned the glad wild way,</l>
              <l>And heart still hovering o’er a song begun,</l>
              <l>And smile that warmed the world with benison,</l>
              <l>Our father, lord long since of lordly rhyme,</l>
              <l>Long since hath haply ridden, when the lime</l>
              <l>Bloomed broad above him, flowering where he came.</l>
              <l>Because thy passage once made warm this clime,</l>
              <l>Our father Chaucer, here we praise thy name.</l>
            </lg>
            . . . . . . . . . .
            <lg>
              <note place="margin">[p. 10]</note> <l>Each turn of the old wild road whereon we stray,</l>
              <l>Meseems, might bring us face to face with one</l>
              <l>Whom seeing we could not but give thanks, and pray</l>
              <l>For England’s love our father and her son</l>
              <l>To speak with us as once in days long done</l>
              <l>With all men, sage and churl and monk and mime,</l>
              <l>Who knew not as we know the soul sublime,</l>
              <l>That sang for song’s love more than lust of fame.</l>
              <l>Yet, though this be not, yet, in happy time,</l>
              <l>Our father Chaucer, here we praise thy name.</l>
            </lg>
            
            <lg>
              <l>Friend, even as bees about the flowering thyme,</l>
              <l>Years crowd on years, till hoar decay begrime</l>
              <l>Names once beloved; but, seeing the sun the same,</l>
              <l>As birds of autumn fain to praise the prime,</l>
              <l>Our father Chaucer, here we praise thy name.</l>
            </lg>
          </seg>
        </ab>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>