<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="part3_p133_a2">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>1883, Henry Charles Coote. Chaucer's Ten-Syllable Verse.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="DS">Devani Singh</name>
          <resp>Principal investigator of the project. Supervision of the workflow and control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="EL">Elina Leblanc</name>
          <resp>Data modelling, OCR correction, text encoding and uploading in the database.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="JS">Jordan Skinner</name>
          <resp>Corpus enhacement and verification of data accuracy. Control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Project SNSF "Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities" (n°225925)</publisher>
        <authority>Department of English Language and Literature, Faculty of Humanities, University of Geneva</authority>
        <address>
          <addrLine>12, boulevard des Philosophes</addrLine>
          <addrLine>1205 Genève</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY</licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author cert="high" role="M" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/66849802">Coote, Henry Charles</author>
            <date cert="high" when="1883">1883</date>
            <title level="a">Chaucer's Ten-Syllable Verse.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion</title>
            <author>Spurgeon, Caroline</author>
            <note>We used the digitizations made by Google for the University of Michigan (Public Domain, Google-Digitized). The facsimile can be found on HathiTrust.<ptr target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015066185086"/></note>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
              <publisher>University Press</publisher>
              <date>1925</date>
            </imprint>
            <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="part">I</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page">133-134</biblScope>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The digital part of the SNSF project 'Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities' aims to create the first open-access database dedicated to the criticism and reception of Chaucer throughout history. It draws on the compilation and cataloguing work carried out by Professor Caroline Spurgeon (1869–1942) and collected in 'Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion'. This work consists of three volumes and a supplement, which will be systematically transcribed, corrected, enriched, encoded and published online, in order to facilitate future research and bring new perspectives to light.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>The original spelling and punctuation are retained. Meaningful layouts are reproduced, i.e. verses, printed marginalia, dots lines, tables, etc. However, we do not consider, the line breaks for prose, the columns or the curly brackets. The same rules apply for special characters and glyphs. Otiose letters are normalised, as well as spaces before punctuation marks.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="FoNDUE" version="0.1">
          <label>FoNDUE</label>
          <ptr target="https://fondue.unige.ch/"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#criticism" target="#praised"/>
        <catRef scheme="#works" target="#troilus"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2026-05-21" who="#EL">Creation of the TEI file and enrichment of data</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="allusion">
        <milestone unit="page" n="133"/>
        
        <ab type="imprint">1883. Coote, Henry Charles. <hi rend="italic">Chaucer's Ten-Syllable Verse</hi>, [in] The Antiquary, July 1883, vol. viii, pp. 5-8.</ab>
        
        <ab type="quotation">
          <seg><note place="margin">[p. 5]</note> Chaucer's <hi rend="italic">Troilus</hi> was not only the first heroic poem and
              the first real display of poetic genius in the language of
              mediæval England, but was the starting-point and departure
              
              <milestone unit="page" n="134"/>
              
              from which English metre took its best and still prevailing
              form. . . .</seg>
              <seg><note place="margin">[p. 7]</note> At the very threshold of his task <add>[that of rendering the
              <hi rend="italic">Filostrato</hi> into English]</add> he had a problem to solve. . . .
              There was no English verse at all fit for the transfer of the
              Italian. He must accordingly invent a new one. . . .</seg>
              <seg>He knew of two metres only, always excepting those used for
              ballads and such like, which were of course out of the question
              here. Of these two metres, one was too short as the other was
              too long for his taste. I mean, of course, the eight-syllabled
              distichs of himself and Gower, and the popular twelve syllable
              <note place="margin">[p. 8]</note> verse such as is exhibited in the rough tale of Gamelin. . . .</seg>
              <seg>He therefore elected to invent for the nonce an entirely new
              metre of his own, and to apply it to his new task. There was
              a mean between eight and twelve, viz. ten. He accordingly
              invented a verse of ten syllables with varying and appropriate
              cæsuræ; and utilized his new invention by translating the
              Filostrato into it; and posterity ratified his choice by adopting
              it as the only verse to be employed upon themes either great
              or graceful. . . .</seg>
              <seg>The consequences of this invention of the ten-syllable metre
              it is impossible to exaggerate or over-estimate. The obvious
              outcome of it is simply this and no other: without it we
              should have had no Shakespeare, Milton, Dryden, or Pope, in
              the sense in which we now have these great masters. To
              convince us of this, we have only to imagine <hi rend="italic">Othello</hi> and
              <hi rend="italic">Hamlet</hi>, not as we now have them through the remote leadership 
              of Chaucer in a verse framed upon his model, but told
              either in the lilting measure of Calderon, or the drawling
              Alexandrines of France. . . . Of course Milton must have
              been better than Cædmon, and Pope would have done his best
              to surpass Butler even in his own light measure, but that is all.</seg>
              <seg>From all this Chaucer saved English literature and the
              English race. . . .</seg>
        </ab>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
