<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/FNS-Spurgeon/4-TEI-Encoding/refs/heads/main/odd/tei_chaucerAllusions.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="part3_p126_a1">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>1880, Matthew Arnold. The Study of Poetry.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="DS">Devani Singh</name>
          <resp>Principal investigator of the project. Supervision of the workflow and control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="EL">Elina Leblanc</name>
          <resp>Data modelling, OCR correction, text encoding and uploading in the database.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="JS">Jordan Skinner</name>
          <resp>Corpus enhacement and verification of data accuracy. Control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Project SNSF "Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities" (n°225925)</publisher>
        <authority>Department of English Language and Literature, Faculty of Humanities, University of Geneva</authority>
        <address>
          <addrLine>12, boulevard des Philosophes</addrLine>
          <addrLine>1205 Genève</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY</licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author cert="high" role="M" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/73868557">Arnold, Matthew</author>
            <date cert="high" when="1880">1880</date>
            <title level="a">The Study of Poetry.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion</title>
            <author>Spurgeon, Caroline</author>
            <note>We used the digitizations made by Google for the University of Michigan (Public Domain, Google-Digitized). The facsimile can be found on HathiTrust.<ptr target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015066185086"/></note>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
              <publisher>University Press</publisher>
              <date>1925</date>
            </imprint>
            <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="part">III</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page" source="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015066185086?urlappend=%3Bseq=452">126-130</biblScope>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The digital part of the SNSF project 'Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities' aims to create the first open-access database dedicated to the criticism and reception of Chaucer throughout history. It draws on the compilation and cataloguing work carried out by Professor Caroline Spurgeon (1869–1942) and collected in 'Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion'. This work consists of three volumes and a supplement, which will be systematically transcribed, corrected, enriched, encoded and published online, in order to facilitate future research and bring new perspectives to light.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>The original spelling and punctuation are retained. Meaningful layouts are reproduced, i.e. verses, printed marginalia, dots lines, tables, etc. However, we do not consider, the line breaks for prose, the columns or the curly brackets. The same rules apply for special characters and glyphs. Otiose letters are normalised, as well as spaces before punctuation marks.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="FoNDUE" version="0.1">
          <label>FoNDUE</label>
          <ptr target="https://fondue.unige.ch/"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#criticism" target="#general"/>
        <catRef scheme="#criticism" target="#burns"/>
        <catRef scheme="#criticism" target="#praised"/>
        <catRef scheme="#works" target="#prioressTale"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2026-05-21" who="#EL">Creation of the TEI file and enrichment of data</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="allusion">
        <milestone unit="page" n="126"/>
        
        <ab type="imprint">1880. Arnold, Matthew. <hi rend="italic">The Study of Poetry</hi>, [the General Introduction to The English Poets, 1880, edited by T. H. Ward], pp. xxxi-xxxvi, xliv, xlv. [Reprinted in <hi rend="italic">Essays in Criticism</hi>, 2nd ser., 1888, pp. 26-34, 49-51.]</ab>
        
        <ab type="quotation">
          <seg><note place="margin">[p. xxxi]</note> But in the fourteenth century there comes an Englishman
              nourished on this poetry <add>[French romance-poetry]</add>, taught his
              trade by this poetry, getting words, rhyme, metre from this
              poetry; for even of that stanza which the Italians used, and
              which Chaucer derived immediately from the Italians, the basis
              and suggestion was probably given in France. Chaucer (I
              have already named him) fascinated his contemporaries, but so
              too did Christian of Troyes and Wolfram of Eschenbach.
              Chaucer's power of fascination, however, is enduring; his
              poetical importance does not need the assistance of the
              historic estimate; it is real. He is a genuine source of joy
              and strength, which is flowing still for us and will flow
              always. He will be read, as time goes on, far more generally
              than he is read now. His language is a cause of difficulty to
              us, but so also, and I think in quite as great a degree, is the
              language of Burns. In Chaucer's case, as in that of Burns, it
              is a difficulty to be unhesitatingly accepted and overcome.</seg>
              <seg>If we ask ourselves wherein consists the immense 
              superiority of Chaucer's poetry over the romance poetry—why
              it is that in passing from this to Chaucer we suddenly feel
              ourselves to be in another world, we shall find that his
              
              <milestone unit="page" n="127"/>
              
              superiority is both in the substance of his poetry and in the
              <note place="margin">[p. xxxii]</note> style of his poetry. His superiority in substance is given by
              his large, free, simple, clear yet kindly view of human life,—
              so unlike the total want, in the romance-poets, of all intelligent 
              command of it. Chaucer has not their helplessness; he
              has gained the power to survey the world from a central, a
              truly human point of view. We have only to call to mind
              the Prologue of <hi rend="italic">The Canterbury Tales</hi>. The right comment
              upon it is Dryden's 'It is sufficient to say, according to the
              proverb, that here is God’s plenty.' And again: 'He is a
              perpetual fountain of good sense.' It is by a large, free,
              sound representation of things, that poetry, this high criticism
              of life, has truth of substance.</seg>
              <seg>Of his style and manner, if we think first of the romance-
              poetry and then of Chaucer's divine liquidness of diction, his
              divine fluidity of movement, it is difficult to speak temperately.
              They are irresistible, and justify all the rapture with which
              his successors speak of his "gold dewdrops of speech."
              Johnson misses the point entirely when he finds fault with
              Dryden for ascribing to Chaucer the first refinement of our
              numbers, and says that Gower can also show smooth numbers
              and easy rhymes. The refinement of our numbers means
              something far more than this. A nation may have versifiers
              with smooth numbers and easy rhymes, and yet may have
              no real poetry at all. Chaucer is the father of our splendid
              English poetry; he is our 'well of English undefiled,' because
              by the lovely charm of his diction, the lovely charm of his
              movement, he makes an epoch and founds a tradition. In
              Spenser, Shakespeare, Milton, Keats, we can follow the
              tradition of the liquid diction, the fluid movement, of
              Chaucer; at one time it is his liquid diction of which in these
              poets we feel the virtue, and at another time it is his fluid
              movement. And the virtue is irresistible.</seg>
              <seg>[p. xxxiii] . . . I must yet find room for an example of Chaucer's
              virtue. . . . I feel disposed to say that a single line is enough
              to show the charm of Chaucer's verse; that merely one line
              like this—
              <l>'O martyr souded<note><add>[Arnold's note:]</add> The French soudé; soldered, fixed fast.</note> in virginitee!'</l>
              has a virtue of manner and movement such as we shall not
              
              <milestone unit="page" n="128"/>
              
              find in all the verse of romance-poetry;—but this is saying
              nothing. The virtue is such as we shall not find, perhaps, in
              all English poetry, outside the poets whom I have named as
              the special inheritors of Chaucer's tradition. A single line,
              however, is too little if we have not the strain of Chaucer's
              verse well in our memory; let us take a stanza. It is from
              <hi rend="italic">The Prioress’s Tale</hi>, the story of the Christian child murdered
              in a Jewry—
              <l>'My throte is cut unto my nekké-bone</l>
              <l>Saidè this child, and as by way of kinde</l>
              <l>I should have deyd, yea, longè time agone <add>[etc.]</add>.</l>
              Wordsworth has modernised this Tale, and to feel how delicate
              and evanescent is the charm of verse, we have only to read
              Wordsworth's first three lines of this stanza after Chaucer's—
              <l>'My throat is cut unto the bone, I trow,</l>
              <l>Said this young child, and by the law of kind</l>
              <l>I should have died, yea, many hours ago.'</l>
              The charm is departed. It is often said that the power of
              liquidness and fluidity in Chaucer's verse was dependent
              upon a free, a licentious dealing with language such as is now
              impossible; upon a liberty, such as Burns too enjoyed, of
              making words like neck bird, into a dissyllable by adding to
              <note place="margin">[p. xxxiv]</note> them, and words like cause, rhyme, into a dissyllable by sound
              sounding the e mute. It is true that Chaucer's fluidity is
              conjoined with this liberty, and is admirably served by it;
              but we ought not to say that it was dependent upon it. It
              was dependent upon his talent. Other poets with a like
              liberty do not attain to the fluidity of Chaucer; Burns 
              himself does not attain to it. Poets, again, who have a talent
              akin to Chaucer's, such as Shakespeare or Keats, have known
              how to attain to his fluidity without the like liberty.</seg>
              <seg>And yet Chaucer is not one of the great classics. His
              poetry transcends and effaces, easily and without effort, all
              the romance-poetry of Catholic Christendom; it transcends
              and effaces all the English poetry contemporary with it, it
              transcends and effaces all the English poetry subsequent to it
              down to the age of Elizabeth. Of such avail is poetic truth
              of substance, in its natural and necessary union with poetic
              truth of style. And yet, I say, Chaucer is not one of the
              
              <milestone unit="page" n="129"/>
              
              great classics. He has not their accent. What is wanting to
              him is suggested by the mere mention of the name of the first
              great classic of Christendom, the immortal poet who died
              eighty years before Chaucer,—Dante. The accent of such
              verse as
              <l>"In la sua volontade è nostra pace . . ."<note>So quoted by Arnold; the original (<hi rend="italic">Paradiso</hi>, iii, 86) reads: E la sua volontate . . .</note></l>
              is altogether beyond Chaucer's reach; we praise him, but we
              feel that this accent is out of the question for him. It may be
              said that it was necessarily out of the reach of any poet in
              the England of that stage of growth. Possibly; but we are to
              adopt a real, not a historic, estimate of poetry. However, we
              may account for its absence, something is wanting, then, to
              the poetry of Chaucer, which poetry must have before it can
              be placed in the glorious class of the best. And there is no
              doubt what that something is. It is the σπουδαιότης, the
              high and excellent seriousness which Aristotle assigns as one
              <note place="margin">[p. xxxv]</note> of the grand virtues of poetry. The substance of Chaucer's
              poetry, his view of things and his criticism of life, has
              largeness, freedom, shrewdness, benignity; but it has not
              this high seriousness. Homer's criticism of life has it,
              Dante's has it, Shakespeare's has it. It is this chiefly
              which gives to our spirits what they can rest upon; and with
              the increasing demands of our modern ages upon poetry, this
              virtue of giving us what we can rest upon will be more and
              more highly esteemed. A voice from the slums of Paris, fifty
              or sixty years after Chaucer, the voice of poor Villon out of
              his life of riot and crime, has at its happy moments (as, for
              instance, in the last stanza of <hi rend="italic">La Belle Heaulmière</hi>) more of
              this important poetic virtue of seriousness than all the 
              productions of Chaucer. But its apparition in Villon, and in
              men like Villon, is fitful; the greatness of the great poets,
              the power of their criticism of life, is that their virtue is
              sustained.</seg>
              <seg>To our praise, therefore, of Chaucer as a poet there must be
              this limitation; he lacks the high seriousness of the great
              classics, and therefore an important part of their virtue.
              Still, the main fact for us to bear in mind about Chaucer is
              his sterling value according to that real estimate which we
              
              <milestone unit="page" n="130"/>
              
              firmly adopt for all poets. He has poetic truth of substance
              though he has not high poetic seriousness, and corresponding
              to his truth of substance he has an exquisite virtue of style
              and manner. With him is born our real poetry. . . .</seg>
              <seg>The age of Dryden, together with our whole eighteenth
              century which followed it, sincerely believed itself to have
              produced poetical classics of its own, and even to have made
              advance, in poetry, beyond all its predecessors. Dryden
              regards as not seriously disputable the opinion 'that the
              sweetness of English verse was never understood or practised
              by our fathers.'<note><add>[Note (unpublished) added by Dr. Furnivall :]</add> We must recollect that, till
              Tyrwhitt, no decent edition of the Canterbury Tales was accessible, and till Richard
              Morris, none of the Minor Poems. So long as printers and editors disregarded
              Chaucer's final e and printed as his, pieces that he never wrote, it was impossible
              for any readers to appreciate his poetic powers.—F. J. F.</note> Cowley could see nothing at all in Chaucer's
              poetry. Dryden heartily admired it, and, as we have seen,
              praised its matter admirably; but of its exquisite manner and
              movement all he can find to say is that 'there is the rude
              sweetness of a Scotch tune in it, which is natural and pleasing,
              though not perfect.' Addison, wishing to praise Chaucer's
              numbers, compares them with Dryden's own. And all through
              the eighteenth century, and down even to our own times, the
              stereotyped phrase of approbation for good verse found in our
              early poetry has been, that it even approached the verse of
              Dryden, Addison, Pope and Johnson. . . .</seg>
              <seg><note place="margin">[p. xliv]</note> Burns, like Chaucer, comes short of the high seriousness of
              the great classics. . . . Yet we may say of him <add>[Burns]</add>, as of
              Chaucer, that of life and the world, as they come before
              <note place="margin">[p. xlv]</note> him, his view is large, free, shrewd, benignant,—truly poetic,
              therefore; and his manner of rendering what he sees is to
              match. But we must note, at the same time, his great difference 
              from Chaucer. The freedom of Chaucer is heightened in
              Burns, by a fiery, reckless energy; the benignity of Chaucer
              deepens, in Burns, into an overwhelming sense of the pathos
              of things;—of the pathos of human nature, the pathos, also,
              of non-human nature. Instead of the fluidity of Chaucer's
              manner, the manner of Burns has spring, bounding swiftness.
              Burns is by far the greater force, though he has perhaps
              less charm. The world of Chaucer is fairer, richer, more
              significant than that of Burns.</seg>
        </ab>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>