<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/FNS-Spurgeon/4-TEI-Encoding/refs/heads/main/odd/tei_chaucerAllusions.rng?token=GHSAT0AAAAAAD6JFEDD7ZTYLUQNLFLI3IJI2QWZJSA" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="part3_p133_a1">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>1881, Henry Poole. Westminster Abbey: A Study on Poets' Corner.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="DS">Devani Singh</name>
          <resp>Principal investigator of the project. Supervision of the workflow and control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="EL">Elina Leblanc</name>
          <resp>Data modelling, OCR correction, text encoding and uploading in the database.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="JS">Jordan Skinner</name>
          <resp>Corpus enhacement and verification of data accuracy. Control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Project SNSF "Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities" (n°225925)</publisher>
        <authority>Department of English Language and Literature, Faculty of Humanities, University of Geneva</authority>
        <address>
          <addrLine>12, boulevard des Philosophes</addrLine>
          <addrLine>1205 Genève</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY</licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author cert="high" role="M" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/">Poole, Henry</author>
            <date cert="high" when="1881">1881</date>
            <title level="a">Westminster Abbey: A Study on Poets' Corner.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion</title>
            <author>Spurgeon, Caroline</author>
            <note>We used the digitizations made by Google for the University of Michigan (Public Domain, Google-Digitized). The facsimile can be found on HathiTrust.<ptr target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015066185086"/></note>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
              <publisher>University Press</publisher>
              <date>1925</date>
            </imprint>
            <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="part">I</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page">133</biblScope>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The digital part of the SNSF project 'Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities' aims to create the first open-access database dedicated to the criticism and reception of Chaucer throughout history. It draws on the compilation and cataloguing work carried out by Professor Caroline Spurgeon (1869–1942) and collected in 'Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion'. This work consists of three volumes and a supplement, which will be systematically transcribed, corrected, enriched, encoded and published online, in order to facilitate future research and bring new perspectives to light.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>The original spelling and punctuation are retained. Meaningful layouts are reproduced, i.e. verses, printed marginalia, dots lines, tables, etc. However, we do not consider, the line breaks for prose, the columns or the curly brackets. The same rules apply for special characters and glyphs. Otiose letters are normalised, as well as spaces before punctuation marks.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="FoNDUE" version="0.1">
          <label>FoNDUE</label>
          <ptr target="https://fondue.unige.ch/"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#biography" target="#tomb-epitath"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2026-05-21" who="#EL">Creation of the TEI file and enrichment of data</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="allusion">
        <milestone unit="page" n="133"/>
        
        <ab type="imprint">1881. Poole, Henry. <hi rend="italic">Westminster Abbey: A Study on Poets' Corner</hi>, [in] The Antiquary, October 1881, vol. iv, pp. 137, 139.</ab>
        
        <ab type="quotation">
          <seg><note place="margin">[p. 139]</note> Having alluded to the probability that the table-tomb of
              Chaucer was once against the screen of St. Benedict’s Chapel,
              it may not be inopportune here to follow out the probable
              story of it.</seg>
              <seg>The tomb proper is evidently due to the period of the death
              of Chaucer. Its quatre-foils bear his shield of arms, and
              around at least three of the sides with <add>[sic]</add> the verge moulding,
              wvhich probably bore a painted inscription. In 1556, there
              was perhaps some necessity for totally removing the tomb, of
              which advantage was taken by Chaucer's admirer, Nicholas
              Brigham, to place it where it now is, and add to it a handsome,
              though debased, canopy of Purbeck marble, and also a similar
              marble slab, with a new inscription in Latin, that of the
              marble table having become decayed and illegible. This slab
              has undergone great decay and disintegration, so much so as
              to almost totally obscure the inscription, as reported by Neale
              in 1823 <add>[or rather by E. W. Brayley in his <hi rend="italic">History and
              Antiquities of the Abbey Church of St. Peter</hi>, Westminster,
              illustrated by J. P. Neale, 1818-23, vol. ii, 1823, q.v. above]</add>.
              Fifty years' more disintegration followed with still further
              obscuration, when the writer closely scrutinized and cleansed
              the slab, discovering traces of all the letters but four.
              Without any attempt to strengthen the engraving, the lettering
              was developed by painting all the remaining traces with gold¬
              coloured paint, and with the same pigment reproducing the
              four absent letters; and now the inscription of 1558 is quite
              distinct and perfectly durable.</seg>
              <seg>The table of the tomb has lately been fully cleansed of dirt
              and adhesions, beneath which the moulding, as well as much
              of the surface, was found still to retain its original polish,
              which the adhesion had preserved. Now the table displays
              a fine specimen of the best Purbeck marble, which need never
              become dull again.</seg>
        </ab>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
