<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/FNS-Spurgeon/4-TEI-Encoding/refs/heads/main/odd/tei_chaucerAllusions.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="part5_p24_a2">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>1749, Antoine Yart. Idée de la poësie angloise.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="DS">Devani Singh</name>
          <resp>Principal investigator of the project. Supervision of the workflow and control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="EL">Elina Leblanc</name>
          <resp>Data modelling, OCR correction, text encoding and uploading in the database.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="JS">Jordan Skinner</name>
          <resp>Corpus enhacement and verification of data accuracy. Control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Project SNSF "Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities" (n°225925)</publisher>
        <authority>Department of English Language and Literature, Faculty of Humanities, University of Geneva</authority>
        <address>
          <addrLine>12, boulevard des Philosophes</addrLine>
          <addrLine>1205 Genève</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY</licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author cert="high" role="M" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12657165">Yart, Antoine</author>
            <date cert="high" when="1749">1749</date>
            <title level="a">Idée de la poësie angloise, ou Traduction des meilleurs Poëtes Anglois, qui n’ont point encore paru dans notre Langue, avec un jugement sur leurs Ouvrages, &amp; une comparaison de leurs Poësies avec celles des Auteurs anciens &amp; modernes.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion</title>
            <author>Spurgeon, Caroline</author>
            <note>We used the digitizations made by Google for the University of Michigan (Public Domain, Google-Digitized). The facsimile can be found on HathiTrust.<ptr target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015066184931"/></note>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
              <publisher>University Press</publisher>
              <date>1925</date>
            </imprint>
            <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="part">V</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page" source="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015066184931?urlappend=%3Bseq=162">24-26</biblScope>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The digital part of the SNSF project 'Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities' aims to create the first open-access database dedicated to the criticism and reception of Chaucer throughout history. It draws on the compilation and cataloguing work carried out by Professor Caroline Spurgeon (1869–1942) and collected in 'Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion'. This work consists of three volumes and a supplement, which will be systematically transcribed, corrected, enriched, encoded and published online, in order to facilitate future research and bring new perspectives to light.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>The original spelling and punctuation are retained. Meaningful layouts are reproduced, i.e. verses, printed marginalia, dots lines, tables, etc. However, we do not consider, the line breaks for prose, the columns or the curly brackets. The same rules apply for special characters and glyphs. Otiose letters are normalised, as well as spaces before punctuation marks.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="FoNDUE" version="0.1">
          <label>FoNDUE</label>
          <ptr target="https://fondue.unige.ch/"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="fr">French</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#biography" target="#french"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2026-06-29" who="#EL">Creation of the TEI file and enrichment of data</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="allusion">
        <milestone unit="page" n="24"/>
        
        <ab type="imprint">1749. Yart, Antoine, Abbé [de Rouen]. <hi rend="italic">Idée de la poësie angloise, ou Traduction des meilleurs Poëtes Anglois, qui n’ont point encore paru dans notre Langue, avec un jugement sur leurs Ouvrages, &amp; une comparaison de leurs Poësies avec celles des Auteurs anciens &amp; modernes.</hi> A Paris, chez Claude Briasson ... 2 tomes, 1749.</ab>
        
        <ab type="quotation">
          <seg><note place="margin">[tom. i, p. xix]</note> <add>[Abridgement of the life of John Philips]</add>, écrite en anglois,
            par M. George Sewell, éditeur de ses Ouvrages.</seg>
          
          <seg>. . . à l’exemple de Milton, son Auteur favori, il cherchoit
            à s’enrichir des termes propres, expressifs, harmonieux du
            vieux langage. . . . Dans ce dessein, il lut Chaucer &amp;
            Spenser.</seg>
            
          <seg><add>[Note by Yart.]</add> Chaucer vécut au milieu du quatorzième
            siècle; il mourut en 1400, il a composé un assez grand
            nombre de Contes; ses Compatriotes admirent l’enjouement 
            &amp; la naïveté de ses narrations; mais son langage
            est tellement vieilli, que les Anglois ne l’entendent presque
            plus; il faisoit des vers fort enjoués, &amp; il sçavoit les
            Mathématiques; il fut surnommé l’Homère Anglois; son Tombeau
            est à Westminster: on l’a rétabli en 1550.</seg>
            
          <lb/>. . . . . . . . . .
            
          <seg><note place="margin">[p. xxiij-xxiv]</note> <add>[Abridgement of the life of Philips, by Sewell.]</add> Simon
              Harcourt, Lord Chancelier d’Angleterre lui a élevé à Westminster un mausolée auprès de celui de Chaucer. . . .</seg>
          
          <lb/>. . . . . . . . . .
            
            
          <seg><note place="margin">[p. xxvij]</note> <add>[Abridgement of the life of Philips, continued,—epitaph]</add>
              Qu’il lui soit donc permis, ô Chaucer, Père de la Poësie
              
              <milestone unit="page" n="25"/>
              
              Angloise, quoiqu’il n’ait pas suivi les Loix (a)<note>(a) <add>[Note by Yart.]</add> Milton fut le premier Poëte
                d’Angleterre qui substitua aux Vers rimés, inventés par
                Chaucer, les Vers blancs ou non rimés. Philips, &amp; plusieurs
                autres Poètes, ont imité Milton dans ce nouveau genre de
                Poësie. . . .</note> que vous avez
              données à la versification, de fermer un des côtés de votre
              Tombeau, il ne deshonorera pas le Chœur des Poëtes qui
              entourent vos cendres.
              <lg>
                <l>Fas fit hinc</l>
                <l>Auso licet à tuâ metrorum lege dicedere,</l>
                <l>O Poësis Anglicanæ Pater, atque conditor Chaucere,</l>
                <l>Aeternum tibi latus claudere:</l>
                <l>Vatum certè cineres, tuos undique stipantium;</l>
                <l>Non dedecebit chorum.</l>
              </lg>
          </seg>
           
          <lb/>. . . . . . . . . .
            
          <seg><note place="margin">[tom. ii, d. 77]</note> On va voir parottre Chaucer &amp; Spencer, ensuite Cowley,
            Milton, Denham, &amp; enfin Waller, Roscommon, Dryden,
            Congreve &amp; Montagu, on verra naître la Poësie Angloise
            avec les premiers, se former avec les seconds, &amp; se polir avec
            les derniers.</seg>
            
          <lb/>. . . . . . . . . . .
            
          <seg><note place="margin">[p. 80]</note> Histoire abrégée des plus grands poëtes anglois, par
            Joseph Addison, à monsieur Henry Sacheverell.</seg>
          
          <seg type="editorial">[A translation follows from Addison’s Account of the greatest English
            poets, 1694. Yart translates thus the verses referring to Chaucer.]</seg>
            
          <seg>Vous voulez, cher Sacheverell, que je parcoure les siècles
            qui se sont écoulés depuis Chaucer jusqu’à Dryden. . . .</seg>
            
          <seg><note place="margin">[p. 81]</note> Nos stupides ayeux étoient plongés depuis long-tems dans
            un sommeil profond; leur âme insensible, n’étoit point émue
            <note place="margin">[p. 82]</note> par l’enthousiasme des neuf sœurs, lorsque Chaucer parut;
            Poëte naïf, il fit divers Contes en Vers &amp; en Prose, mais le
            tems a porté sa rouille sur ses Ecrits, défiguré son langage,
            obscurci son esprit; il s’efforce d’égayer ses vers grossiers
            par des plaisanteries, il ne peut venir à bout de divertir ses
            lecteurs.</seg>
            
          <lb/>. . . . . . . . . . .
            
          <seg><note place="margin">[p. 107]</note> <add>[<hi rend="italic">The Progress of Poetry</hi>, by Lady Mary Wortley Montagu.]</add>
            . . . Chaucer, le premier, ouvrit sa veine comique, il en fit
            couler ses contes plaisans &amp; naïfs: des beautés sans parure,
            
            <milestone unit="page" n="26"/>
            
            ornent ses vers sans art; son style est grossier, mai ses
            pensées sont fortes.</seg>
        </ab>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>