<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/FNS-Spurgeon/4-TEI-Encoding/refs/heads/main/odd/tei_chaucerAllusions.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="part5_p26_a1">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>1749, Jean Arnold Trochereau de La Berlière. Choix de Différens morceaux de Poësie traduits de l’Anglois.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="DS">Devani Singh</name>
          <resp>Principal investigator of the project. Supervision of the workflow and control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="EL">Elina Leblanc</name>
          <resp>Data modelling, OCR correction, text encoding and uploading in the database.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="JS">Jordan Skinner</name>
          <resp>Corpus enhacement and verification of data accuracy. Control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Project SNSF "Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities" (n°225925)</publisher>
        <authority>Department of English Language and Literature, Faculty of Humanities, University of Geneva</authority>
        <address>
          <addrLine>12, boulevard des Philosophes</addrLine>
          <addrLine>1205 Genève</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY</licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author cert="high" role="M" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/71177003">Trochereau de La Berlière, Jean Arnold</author>
            <date cert="high" when="1749">1749</date>
            <title level="a">Choix de Différens morceaux de Poësie traduits de l’Anglois.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion</title>
            <author>Spurgeon, Caroline</author>
            <note>We used the digitizations made by Google for the University of Michigan (Public Domain, Google-Digitized). The facsimile can be found on HathiTrust.<ptr target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015066184931"/></note>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
              <publisher>University Press</publisher>
              <date>1925</date>
            </imprint>
            <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="part">V</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page" source="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015066184931?urlappend=%3Bseq=164">26-27</biblScope>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The digital part of the SNSF project 'Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities' aims to create the first open-access database dedicated to the criticism and reception of Chaucer throughout history. It draws on the compilation and cataloguing work carried out by Professor Caroline Spurgeon (1869–1942) and collected in 'Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion'. This work consists of three volumes and a supplement, which will be systematically transcribed, corrected, enriched, encoded and published online, in order to facilitate future research and bring new perspectives to light.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>The original spelling and punctuation are retained. Meaningful layouts are reproduced, i.e. verses, printed marginalia, dots lines, tables, etc. However, we do not consider, the line breaks for prose, the columns or the curly brackets. The same rules apply for special characters and glyphs. Otiose letters are normalised, as well as spaces before punctuation marks.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="FoNDUE" version="0.1">
          <label>FoNDUE</label>
          <ptr target="https://fondue.unige.ch/"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="fr">French</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass/>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2026-06-29" who="#EL">Creation of the TEI file and enrichment of data</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="allusion">
        <milestone unit="page" n="26"/>
        
        <ab type="imprint">1749. Trochereau de la Berlière, Jean Arnold. <hi rend="italic">Choix de Différens morceaux de Poësie traduits de l’Anglois, par M. Trochereau</hi> . . . à Paris, 1749 [e.g. <hi rend="italic">Essay on Poetry</hi>, by Buckingham, <hi rend="italic">Essay on Translated Verse</hi>, by Roscommon, and the <hi rend="italic">Temple of Fame</hi>, by Pope].</ab>
        
        <ab type="quotation">
          <seg><note place="margin">[p. 20]</note><add>[Note on Denham.]</add> <add>[Il]</add> fut enterré à Westmunster <add>[sic]</add> près de Chaucer, Spenser &amp; Cowley. . . .</seg>
            
          <seg><note place="margin">[p. 21]</note><add>[Note on Couoley.]</add> Il fut enterré . . . près des cendres de Spencer &amp; Chaucer.</seg>
            
          <lb/>. . . . . . . . . . .
            
          <seg type="editorial"><note place="margin">[p. 117]</note> [Forewords by Trochereau on the <hi rend="italic">Temple of Fame</hi> by
            Pope; based on the note printed by Pope himself at the head of his <hi rend="italic">Temple of Fame</hi>.]</seg>
            
          <seg>M. Pope dit qu’il en a puisé
            l'idée dans le Poëme de Chaucer, intitulé le <hi rend="italic">Palais de la
            Renommée</hi>. Mais le dessein, dit-il, n’en est pas le même;
            les descriptions de presque toutes les pensées m’appartiennent.
            . . . Si quelqu’un vouloit comparer ce Poëme à celui de
            Chaucer, il peut commencer au troisième Livre <hi rend="italic">de la
            Renommée</hi>, car il n’y a rien dans les deux premiers qui
            réponde à leur titre.</seg>
            
          <seg><add>[Note by Trochereau.]</add> Il est si souvent parlé de Chaucer,
            dans les Livres Anglois, que j’ai cru qu’on verroit avec
            quelque plaisir les circonstances de sa vie.</seg>
            
          <seg>Geoffroi Chaucer, Poëte distingué du xiv siècle, nâquit
            dans la 3e année du règne d’Edouard III, l’an 1328. Il fut
            d’abord Page de ce Roi; qui le combla de biens &amp; de faveurs.
            Il le fit Gentilhomme de sa Chambre, &amp; lui donna une pension
            considérable. Ses talens le firent employer en qualité de
            Négociateur dans différentes Cours: il fut envoyé à Gènes
            pour traiter avec le Doge de cette République, &amp; peu de
            tems après il fut député à la Cour de France.</seg>
            
          <seg>Les règnes malheureux de Richard iii <add>[sic]</add> &amp; de Henry IV.
            succédèrent aux beaux jours du règne d’Edouard III. Chaucer
            éprouva alors différentes révolutions dans sa fortune. Il
            mourut à 72 ans le 25 Octobre 1400, &amp; il fut enterré dans
            l’Abbaye de Westmunster.</seg>
            
          <seg>En 1555 ou 1556. M. Nicolas Bryham <add>[sic]</add>, Gentilhomme
            d’Oxford, lui fit élever à ses propres dépens un beau
            
            <milestone unit="page" n="27"/>
            
            monument dans la même Abbaye, &amp; y fit graver cette
            Inscription :
            <lg>
              <l>M. S.</l>
              <l>Qui fuit Anglorum vates ter maximas <add>[sic]</add> olim,</l>
              <l>Gofrigidus <add>[sic]</add> Chaucer conditur hoc tumulo</l>
              <l>Annum si quaras Domini, si tempora vitæ,</l>
              <l>Ecce notæ subsunt, quæ tibi cuncta notant.</l>
              <l>25 Octob. 1400.</l>
            </lg>
          </seg>
            
          <seg>Milton le mettoit au rang des plus grands Poëtes. M.
            Dryden dit dans la Préface qu’il a mise à la tête de ses
            Fables, qu’on doit le regarder comme le père de la Poësie
            Angloise. Qu’il doit être aussi estimé en Angleterre
            qu’Homère l’étoit chez les Grecs, &amp; Virgile chez les Latins ;
            qu’il suit la nature par-tout ; mais que jamais il ne la passe,
            &amp; que sçachant ce qu’il falloit dire, il sçavoit aussi où il
            falloit s’arrêter, que ses vers ne sont pas harmonieux, mais
            qu’ils étoient à l’unisson des oreilles de son siècle.</seg>
            
          <seg>Il a décrit les Contes de ses Pèlerins de Cantorberi, les
            caractères, les mœurs &amp; les vices des son tems. Il a composé
            beaucoup d’autres ouvrages pleins d’enjouement &amp; de naïveté ;
            il égaïe souvent ses lecteurs aux dépens des moines &amp; de la
            pudeur. Son langage a tellement vieilli que les Anglois
            même ne l’entendent presque plus : Voici ce que dit M. Pope
            à ce sujet dans son <hi rend="italic">Essai sur la Critique</hi>.</seg>
            
          <seg>'La réputation passe promptement, et douze lustres sont le
            plus long terme dont on puisse se flater. Nos fils voyent
            décheoir le langage de leurs pères, et ce que Chaucer est pour
            nous, Dryden le sera pour eux.' (Traduction de M. Sillouet.)</seg>
        </ab>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>