<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/FNS-Spurgeon/4-TEI-Encoding/refs/heads/main/odd/tei_chaucerAllusions.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="part5_p91_a6">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>1886, Édouard Drumont. La France Juive.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="DS">Devani Singh</name>
          <resp>Principal investigator of the project. Supervision of the workflow and control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="EL">Elina Leblanc</name>
          <resp>Data modelling, OCR correction, text encoding and uploading in the database.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="JS">Jordan Skinner</name>
          <resp>Corpus enhacement and verification of data accuracy. Control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Project SNSF "Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities" (n°225925)</publisher>
        <authority>Department of English Language and Literature, Faculty of Humanities, University of Geneva</authority>
        <address>
          <addrLine>12, boulevard des Philosophes</addrLine>
          <addrLine>1205 Genève</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY</licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author cert="high" role="M" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/44319328">Drumont, Édouard</author>
            <date cert="high" when="1886">1886</date>
            <title level="a">La France Juive.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion</title>
            <author>Spurgeon, Caroline</author>
            <note>We used the digitizations made by Google for the University of Michigan (Public Domain, Google-Digitized). The facsimile can be found on HathiTrust.<ptr target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015066184931"/></note>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
              <publisher>University Press</publisher>
              <date>1925</date>
            </imprint>
            <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="part">V</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page">91-92</biblScope>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The digital part of the SNSF project 'Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities' aims to create the first open-access database dedicated to the criticism and reception of Chaucer throughout history. It draws on the compilation and cataloguing work carried out by Professor Caroline Spurgeon (1869–1942) and collected in 'Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion'. This work consists of three volumes and a supplement, which will be systematically transcribed, corrected, enriched, encoded and published online, in order to facilitate future research and bring new perspectives to light.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>The original spelling and punctuation are retained. Meaningful layouts are reproduced, i.e. verses, printed marginalia, dots lines, tables, etc. However, we do not consider, the line breaks for prose, the columns or the curly brackets. The same rules apply for special characters and glyphs. Otiose letters are normalised, as well as spaces before punctuation marks.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="FoNDUE" version="0.1">
          <label>FoNDUE</label>
          <ptr target="https://fondue.unige.ch/"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="fr">French</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#works" target="#prioressTale"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2026-06-29" who="#EL">Creation of the TEI file and enrichment of data</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="allusion">
        <milestone unit="page" n="91"/>
        
        <ab type="imprint">1886. Drumont, Édouard. <hi rend="italic">La France Juive</hi>, Paris, 1886, tome ii, pp. 381-91.</ab>
        
        <ab type="quotation">
          <seg><note place="margin">[p. 381]</note>En constatant la persistance de ces sentiments de haine
            chez les Juifs, il est impossible de ne point parler un peu
            
            <milestone unit="page" n="92"/>
            
            longuement de ce sacrifice sanglant, cette accusation mille
            fois prouvée <add>[qu’ils tuèrent les petits enfants]</add> . . .</seg>
          
          <seg><note place="margin">[p. 383]</note>Il n’est pas un écrivain du Moyen Age qui ne parle de
            ces faits comme d’une chose ordinaire. . . .</seg>
            
          <seg><note place="margin">[p. 384]</note>Mais c’est Chaucer peut-être qui est le plus intéressant à
            consulter sur ce point. Le poète du XVe siècle <add>[sic]</add>, qui
            repose à Westminster et sur la tombe duquel on a gravé
            quelques jolis vers de la <hi rend="italic">Fleur et de la Feuille</hi>, fut le peintre
            exact des mœurs de son temps. <hi rend="italic">Les Contes de Canterbury</hi>
            sont une sorte de Décaméron auquel sert de prétexte et
            <note place="margin">[p. 385]</note>de cadre le pèlerinage . . . Réunis par hasard, des pèlerins
            de toutes les conditions . . . conviennent pour charmer
            l’ennui du chemin de conter tour à tour une histoire.
            Rien n’est plus touchant que le Récit de la Prieure. Il est
            vraiment d’un charme si profond dans son mysticisme
            féminin, que nous le traduisons presque en entier, en nous
            efforçant de respecter, autant que possible, la naïveté de
            l’original. <add>[There follows a translation of the <hi rend="italic">Prioresses
            Tale</hi>, pp. 385-90.]</add></seg>
        </ab>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
