<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/FNS-Spurgeon/4-TEI-Encoding/refs/heads/main/odd/tei_chaucerAllusions.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="part5_p111_a2">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>1908, Geoffrey Chaucer. Les Contes de Canterbury de Geoffroy Chaucer. Traduction française, avec une introduction et des notes. ...</title>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="DS">Devani Singh</name>
          <resp>Principal investigator of the project. Supervision of the workflow and control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="EL">Elina Leblanc</name>
          <resp>Data modelling, OCR correction, text encoding and uploading in the database.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="JS">Jordan Skinner</name>
          <resp>Corpus enhacement and verification of data accuracy. Control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Project SNSF "Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities" (n°225925)</publisher>
        <authority>Department of English Language and Literature, Faculty of Humanities, University of Geneva</authority>
        <address>
          <addrLine>12, boulevard des Philosophes</addrLine>
          <addrLine>1205 Genève</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY</licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author cert="high" role="M" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100185203">Geoffrey Chaucer</author>
            <date cert="high" when="1908">1908</date>
            <title level="a">Les Contes de Canterbury de Geoffroy Chaucer. Traduction française, avec une introduction et des notes. ...</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion</title>
            <author>Spurgeon, Caroline</author>
            <note>We used the digitizations made by Google for the University of Michigan (Public Domain, Google-Digitized). The facsimile can be found on HathiTrust.<ptr target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015066184931"/></note>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
              <publisher>University Press</publisher>
              <date>1925</date>
            </imprint>
            <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="part">V</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page">111-113</biblScope>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The digital part of the SNSF project 'Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities' aims to create the first open-access database dedicated to the criticism and reception of Chaucer throughout history. It draws on the compilation and cataloguing work carried out by Professor Caroline Spurgeon (1869–1942) and collected in 'Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion'. This work consists of three volumes and a supplement, which will be systematically transcribed, corrected, enriched, encoded and published online, in order to facilitate future research and bring new perspectives to light.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>The original spelling and punctuation are retained. Meaningful layouts are reproduced, i.e. verses, printed marginalia, dots lines, tables, etc. However, we do not consider, the line breaks for prose, the columns or the curly brackets. The same rules apply for special characters and glyphs. Otiose letters are normalised, as well as spaces before punctuation marks.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="FoNDUE" version="0.1">
          <label>FoNDUE</label>
          <ptr target="https://fondue.unige.ch/"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="fr">French</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass/>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2026-06-29" who="#EL">Creation of the TEI file and enrichment of data</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="allusion">
        <milestone unit="page" n="111"/>
        <ab type="imprint">1908. Chaucer, Geoffrey. Les Contes de Canterbury de Geoffroy Chaucer. Traduction française, avec une introduction et des notes. ... Paris, Félix Alcan, 1908.</ab>
        <ab type="quotation">
          <seg>[This appeared as No. 4 bis of the Revue Germanique for Sept. 1906, 1907 and 1908,
and was re-issued in 1 vol. in 1908.]
[p. v] La traduction a été ainsi répartie entre les professeurs
agrégés d’anglais dont les noms suivent :
Prologue Général.—M. Cazamian, professeur adjoint á
l’Université de Bordeaux.
Conte du Chevalier. Ire partie. M. Léon Morel, chargé
de cours à la Sorbonne.
IIe partie.— M. C.-M. Garnier, pro¬
fesseur au lycée Henri IV.
IIIe et IVe parties.— M. Bourgogne,
professeur au lycée Condorcet.
Prologue et Conte du Meunier.— M. Delcourt, professeur au
Iycée de Montpellier.
Prologue et Conte de l’Intendant.
M. Derocquigny, profes¬
Prologue et Conte du Cuisinier.
seur à l’Université de
Lille.
Introduction, Prologue et Conte de l’Homme de Loi.—M. W.
Thomas, professeur à l’Université de Lyon.
Prologue et Conte du Marinier. M. Koszul, professeur au
Prologue et Conte de la Prieure. lycée de Lyon.
Prologue et Conte de Chaucer sur
sire Thopaze.
M. E. Legouis, profes¬
Prologue du Mellibée.
seur à la Sorbonne.
Conte de Chaucer sur Mellibée.—M. Bastide, professeur au
Iycée Charlemagne.
Prologue et Conte du Moine.—M. Charles Petit, professeur
au lycée d’Amiens.
Prologue, Conte et Épilogue du Prêtre de Nonnains.—M. C.
Cestre, maître de conférences à l’Université de Lyon.
Conte et Épilogue du Médecin.
M. Clermont, profes¬
Prologue et Conte du Pardonneur.
seur au Iycée Janson-
de-Sailly.
Prologue de la Femme de Bath.—M. Derocquigny, profes¬
seur à l’Université de Lille.
[p. vi] Conte de la Femme de Bath. M. E. Wahl, professeur au
Prologue et Conte du Frère. Iycée Janson-de -Sailly.
Prologue et Conte du Semoneur.—M. Bauchet, professeur
au lycée d’Évreux.
Prologue et Conte du Clerc.—M. R. Huchon, maître de
conférences à l’Université de Nancy.
Prologue, Conte et Epilogue du Marchand.—M. Lavault,
professeur au lycée Janson-de-Sailly.
Conte et Epilogue de l’Écuyer.—M. Bahans, professeur au
Iycée de Pau.
Prologue et Conte du Franklin.—M. P. Berger, professeur
au Iycée de Bordeaux.
Prologue et Conte de la Seconde Nonne.—M. Vallod, pro¬
fesseur au lycée de Nancy.
Prologue et Conte du Valet du Chanoine.—M. Castelain,
professeur adjoint à l’Université de Poitiers.
Prologue et Conte du Manciple. M. Bastide, professeur au
Prologue et Conte du Curé. Iycée Charlemagne.
[p. vii] Avertissement. Les traducteurs ont adopté les règles
suivantes :
1° Emploi du texte des Contes de Canterbury, publié par
Mr. W. W. Skeat dans son Student's Chaucer . . . le meilleur
texte existant, presque définitif. Ce texte a été suivi fidèle¬
ment, mais non servilement, et les traducteurs ont cru devoir
s’en séparer, en de très rares occasions, surtout en ce qui
concerne la ponctuation adoptée par la critique. . . .
. . . . . . . . . .
2° Notes réduites au strict nécessaire. . . .
 . . . . . . . . . .
3° Traduction linéaire, vers pour vers, d’où un style sans
doute moins coulant, mais en revanche plus fidèle et peut-
être plus savoureux. . . .
. . . . . . . . . .
[p. viii] L’accueil fait à la première moitié de ce livre permet de
croire qu’il vient à son heure et comble une lacune enfin
devenue sensible. Le premier Groupe des Contes, paru en
fascicule dans un numéro supplémentaire de la Revue
Germanique, a été honoré par l’Académie française d’une
partie du prix Langlois. . . .
Il est d’ailleurs difficile de ne pas voir un indice signalé du
progrès des études de langues vivantes chez nous, dans le
nombre, la compétence et le zèle des collaborateurs qui se
sont unis spontanément en vue de mener à bien une œuvre
longue, délicate, exigeant la connaissance de la vieille langue
anglaise, et toute désintéressée.
La Société pour l’Étude des Langues
et Littératures modernes.
[pp. ix.-xxxii.] Introduction, par M. Émile Legouis. [See
below.]</seg>
        </ab>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
