<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/FNS-Spurgeon/4-TEI-Encoding/refs/heads/main/odd/tei_chaucerAllusions.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="part5_p40_a1">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>1813, Jean-Baptiste-Antoine Suard. [Article on Chaucer in the] Biographie Universelle, ancienne et moderne.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="DS">Devani Singh</name>
          <resp>Principal investigator of the project. Supervision of the workflow and control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="EL">Elina Leblanc</name>
          <resp>Data modelling, OCR correction, text encoding and uploading in the database.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="JS">Jordan Skinner</name>
          <resp>Corpus enhacement and verification of data accuracy. Control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Project SNSF "Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities" (n°225925)</publisher>
        <authority>Department of English Language and Literature, Faculty of Humanities, University of Geneva</authority>
        <address>
          <addrLine>12, boulevard des Philosophes</addrLine>
          <addrLine>1205 Genève</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY</licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author cert="high" role="M" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/89808442">Suard, Jean-Baptiste-Antoine</author>
            <date cert="high" when="1813">1813</date>
            <title level="a">[Article on Chaucer in the] Biographie Universelle, ancienne et moderne.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion</title>
            <author>Spurgeon, Caroline</author>
            <note>We used the digitizations made by Google for the University of Michigan (Public Domain, Google-Digitized). The facsimile can be found on HathiTrust.<ptr target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015066184931"/></note>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
              <publisher>University Press</publisher>
              <date>1925</date>
            </imprint>
            <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="part">V</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page" source="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015066184931?urlappend=%3Bseq=178">40-41</biblScope>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The digital part of the SNSF project 'Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities' aims to create the first open-access database dedicated to the criticism and reception of Chaucer throughout history. It draws on the compilation and cataloguing work carried out by Professor Caroline Spurgeon (1869–1942) and collected in 'Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion'. This work consists of three volumes and a supplement, which will be systematically transcribed, corrected, enriched, encoded and published online, in order to facilitate future research and bring new perspectives to light.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>The original spelling and punctuation are retained. Meaningful layouts are reproduced, i.e. verses, printed marginalia, dots lines, tables, etc. However, we do not consider, the line breaks for prose, the columns or the curly brackets. The same rules apply for special characters and glyphs. Otiose letters are normalised, as well as spaces before punctuation marks.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="FoNDUE" version="0.1">
          <label>FoNDUE</label>
          <ptr target="https://fondue.unige.ch/"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="fr">French</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#criticism" target="#thoughtIrregular"/>
        <catRef scheme="#works" target="#criticism"/>
        <catRef scheme="#biography" target="#french"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2026-06-29" who="#EL">Creation of the TEI file and enrichment of data</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="allusion">
        <milestone unit="page" n="40"/>
        
        <ab type="imprint">1813. Suard, Jean-Baptiste-Antoine. [Article on <hi rend="italic">Chaucer</hi> in the] <hi rend="italic">Biographie Universelle, ancienne et moderne</hi>. . . . ouvrage entièrement neuf, redigé par une société de gens de lettres. Paris, 1813, tome viii, pp. 286-89.</ab>
        
        <ab type="quotation">
          <seg type="editorial">[A long biography, with the usual errors due to the
            acceptance of the <hi rend="italic">Testament of Love</hi>, but written with care,
            and indicating some knowledge of the poems of Chaucer.]</seg>
            
          <seg><note place="margin">[p. 287]</note> . . . La <hi rend="italic">Cour d’amour</hi> avait été suivie, peu de temps après,
            du poème de <hi rend="italic">Troïlus et Créséide</hi>, d’<hi rend="italic">Arcile <add>[sic]</add> et Palémon</hi>, de
            la <hi rend="italic">Maison de la Renommée</hi>, etc., ouvrages dont il ne paraît pas
            que l’invention appartienne à Chaucer; mais dont il donne
            quelques-uns pour imités, et dont les autres le sont visiblement,
            soit du <hi rend="italic">Roman de la Rose</hi>, de Boccace, soit de quelques
            auteurs moins célèbres. Il paraît avoir puisé surtout dans
            les ouvrages des troubadours provençaux, qu’il affectionnait
            particulièrement, et auxquels la fierté anglaise lui reproche
            d’avoir emprunté un grand nombre de mots pour les transporter
            dans sa langue, comme il est aisé de le voir par l’abondance
            de mots français qui se trouvent dans ses écrits. Ces
            poésies, dont l’invention, quand elle appartiendrait à Chaucer,
            ne vaudrait pas la peine d’être revendiquée, portent l’empreinte
            du mauvais goût qui régnait alors dans tout l’Europe,
            <note place="margin">[p. 288]</note> <add>[Description of the <hi rend="italic">Court of Love</hi>]</add> . . . Dans <hi rend="italic">Troïlus et
            Créséide</hi>, poëme dont l’action se passe durant le siège de Troie,
            Troïlus est désigné comme un jeune chevalier (knight), et de
            même précisément que l’A est maintenant la première lettre
            de l’alphabet, Créséide était, parmi les dames troyennes, la
            première en beauté.</seg>
            
          <seg>Ses autres ouvrages, tels que la <hi rend="italic">Maison de la Renommée</hi>,
            que Pope a imitée dans son <hi rend="italic">Temple de la Renommée</hi>, et les
            poésies faites en l’honneur du duc et de la duchesse de
            Lancastre, sont, pour la plupart, des rêves, des visions
            allégoriques, mèlés de dissertations morales ou théologiques dans le
            
            <milestone unit="page" n="41"/>
            
            goût du temps; ce qui, outre la difficulté de la langue, rend la
            lecture des ouvrages de Chaucer pénible et ennuyeuse. On y
            trouve cependant de la vérité dans la peinture des caractères
            et une délicatesse de sentiments, qui, dans ce temps là,
            s’alliait assez souvent à la grossièreté des expressions. Les
            Anglais assurent de plus que, malgré l’irrégularité de la
            versification, la poésie de Chaucer ne manque pas d’harmonie;
            et cette irrégularité n’a pas empêché de le regarder comme
            <note place="margin">[p. 289]</note> l’inventeur du vers héroïque anglais. . . . <add>[Chaucer]</add> jouissait
            tranquillement de sa fortune dans le château de Dunnington
            . . . Ce fut là que, dans ses dernières années, il composa celui
            de ses ouvrages qui a conservé le plus de réputation, ses
            <hi rend="italic">Contes de Cantorbéry</hi>, écrits en vers, dans la forme du
            <hi rend="italic">Décaméron</hi> de Boccace, mais dont les sujets, entièrement anglais,
            offrent une grande variété de caractères peints avec la vérité
            propre à ce poète, et une vivacité qu’on ne lui trouve pas
            toujours. Chaucer a eu le sort de tous les écrivains qui ont
            montré du génie dans les premiers temps de la renaissance
            des lettres, lorsque la langue et le goût n’étaient pas encore
            formés. On l’admire et on le loue beaucoup, mais on le
            lit peu.</seg>
            
          <seg>Il est le premier des modernes qui ait fait usage dans la
            poésie de l’esprit et des fictions chevaleresques. Son conte
            de <hi rend="italic">Sir Topaz</hi> est dans le goût de <hi rend="italic">Don Quichotte</hi>.</seg>
          
          <seg type="editorial">[Suard’s article, much abridged, and containing hardly anything of the passages quoted above, was reprinted in the <hi rend="italic">Biographie universelle</hi> of 1833 (6 vols.), of 1838 (6 vols.) and of 1843-7 (Brussels, 21 vols.); and also in the <hi rend="italic">Biographie universelle classique</hi>, 1829.]</seg>
        </ab>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>