<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/FNS-Spurgeon/4-TEI-Encoding/refs/heads/main/odd/tei_chaucerAllusions.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="part5_p29_a1">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>1753-6, Antoine Yart. Idée de la poësie angloise,</title>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="DS">Devani Singh</name>
          <resp>Principal investigator of the project. Supervision of the workflow and control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="EL">Elina Leblanc</name>
          <resp>Data modelling, OCR correction, text encoding and uploading in the database.</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="JS">Jordan Skinner</name>
          <resp>Corpus enhacement and verification of data accuracy. Control of data quality.</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Project SNSF "Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities" (n°225925)</publisher>
        <authority>Department of English Language and Literature, Faculty of Humanities, University of Geneva</authority>
        <address>
          <addrLine>12, boulevard des Philosophes</addrLine>
          <addrLine>1205 Genève</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY</licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author cert="high" role="M" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12657165">Antoine Yart</author>
            <date cert="high" when="1753-6">1753-6</date>
            <title level="a">Idée de la poësie angloise,</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion</title>
            <author>Spurgeon, Caroline</author>
            <note>We used the digitizations made by Google for the University of Michigan (Public Domain, Google-Digitized). The facsimile can be found on HathiTrust.<ptr target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015066184931"/></note>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
              <publisher>University Press</publisher>
              <date>1925</date>
            </imprint>
            <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="part">V</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page">29-30</biblScope>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The digital part of the SNSF project 'Caroline Spurgeon: Chaucer Allusions, Shakespeare's Imagery, and the Digital Humanities' aims to create the first open-access database dedicated to the criticism and reception of Chaucer throughout history. It draws on the compilation and cataloguing work carried out by Professor Caroline Spurgeon (1869–1942) and collected in 'Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion'. This work consists of three volumes and a supplement, which will be systematically transcribed, corrected, enriched, encoded and published online, in order to facilitate future research and bring new perspectives to light.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>The original spelling and punctuation are retained. Meaningful layouts are reproduced, i.e. verses, printed marginalia, dots lines, tables, etc. However, we do not consider, the line breaks for prose, the columns or the curly brackets. The same rules apply for special characters and glyphs. Otiose letters are normalised, as well as spaces before punctuation marks.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="FoNDUE" version="0.1">
          <label>FoNDUE</label>
          <ptr target="https://fondue.unige.ch/"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="fr">French</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#criticism" target="#impiety"/>
        <catRef scheme="#criticism" target="#indecencyFrivolity"/>
        <catRef scheme="#criticism" target="#sublimity"/>
        <catRef scheme="#works" target="#knightTale"/>
        <catRef scheme="#works" target="#knightTale"/>
        <catRef scheme="#works" target="#criticism"/>
        <catRef scheme="#biography" target="#french"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2026-06-29" who="#EL">Creation of the TEI file and enrichment of data</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="allusion">
        <milestone unit="page" n="29"/>
        <ab type="imprint">1753-6. Yart, Antoine. Idée de la poësie angloise, [2nd edition in 8 vols. The two first volumes are an exact reprint of those of the edition of 1749, and the quotations are thus identical], tome iv, p. 261, tome vii (1756), pp. 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 24-32 [Life of Chaucer].</ab>
        <ab type="quotation">
          <seg>Discours sur les Contes. [pp. 4, 5.]
[Chaucer imitated the Italians and also the 'Conteurs' of
Provence.] Ainsi ne cherchez pas plus d’inventions dans
les Poëmes de Chaucer que dans ceux de la Fontaine, mais
si l’invention du fond leur manque, elle est suppléée dans l’un
&amp; dans l’autre par le génie des détails ; mérite plus admirable
peut-être que celui de l’invention.
[Epitome of the life of Chaucer. Yart begins by referring
us to the New Historical and Critical Dictionary made by
the English in imitation of that of Bayle. We are there
informed that the poet lived at the end of the fourteenth
century and the commencement of the fifteenth, in the
reigns of Edward III, Richard II, and of Henry IV, whose
poet and friend he was . . . and that he] contribua beaucoup
par ses intrigues et plus encore par les éloges qu’il fit de
[p. 26] Henri IV, à le faire monter et à l’affirmir sur le trône. . . .
[p. 27] Il s’occupa de sciences et de poésie, tandis qu’il mesuroit
les cieux et qu’il faisoit un savant traité sur l’Astrolabe, il
étudioit les Langues Provençale et Italienne, et il faisoit
passer dans sa Langue, qui était encore informe, les expres¬
sions, les tours et l’harmonie de ces deux langues. . . .
Ce qu’il y a de plus original dans Chaucer, ce sont les
divers caractères des auteurs de ses Contes, intitulés Contes
de Cantorbéry . . . il peignit d’après nature leurs caractères,
leurs habillements, leurs vertus et leurs vices, mais ses
portraits sont si bizarres et si étranges, ses personnages si
désagréables et si indécens, ses satyres si cruelles et si
impies, que, malgré l’art que j'ai tâché de mettre dans ma
traduction, je n’ai pu me flatter de les rendre supportables.
Ses autres contes sont encore plus licencieux que ceux de
nos Poëtes les plus obscènes, je les laisserai par la même
raison dans l’obscurité de leur vieux langage. . . .
[Yart admits, nevertheless, that the poetry of Chaucer]
[p. 29] est, dit-on, aussi facile et aussi naturelle que la prose de
Boccace.
[And he quotes these verses written originally by Voltaire
on Homer; Yart substitutes the name of Chaucer]:
Plein de beautés et de défauts
Le vieux Chaucer a mon estime
Il est, comme tous ses héros
Babillard, outré, mais sublime.
Il est sublime quelquefois, mais il ne l’est pas aussi souvent
qu’Homère.
[Chaucer imitated the Teseide of Boccaccio in 1400. Yart
then quotes the description of this poem by Dryden: 'Ce
[pp. 29- Poème est du genre épique &amp;c. . . .]
30]
[p. 30
note]
[Yart cites] 'la savante Bibliothèque Française de M.
l’Abbé Goujet, tome vii,' [q. v. below, .1755; but, he adds,]
'ce qu’on ne trouve point dans cette Bibliothèque, c’est que
la célèbre Demoiselle de Scudéry a traduit en François selon
Dryden les contes de Chaucer,' &amp;c., &amp;c. [and he quotes all
that Dryden had to say on this subject in his Preface to
the Fables; see above, pt. i, pp. 282-3].
[pp. 33-81] [Translation of the Palamon and Arcite of Dryden.]
[note.
p. 78]
Etait-ce faute de goût ou par amour-propre, que Dryden
[p. 79] mettoit ce Poëme vis-à-vis de l’Iliade &amp; de l’Enéide. J’ai
conservé les principaux faits de ce conte. Il renferme des
impiétés &amp; des obscurités que je n’ai eu garde de traduire,
des longueurs à chaque page que j’ai retranchées, quelques
folies &amp; beaucoup de beaux traits que j’ai tâché de rendre.
Thésée est injuste de condamner ces deux jeunes héros à une
prison horrible, sans qu’ils l’ayent mérité, &amp; cependant ce
Thésée est un assez bon Prince. Arcite a eu tort au com¬
mencement : mais il est si aimable, si généreux, si tendre
dans la suite qu’on lui pardonne ses torts: on le préfère à
Palemon, qui mérite moins que lui d’être heureux. Emilie
n’a presque aucun caractère: elle est dans une inaction
continuelle. Ce Poëme est au moins de 2500 Vers: il y en
a 2000 de superflus: le reste est rempli de beautés; il falloit
rendre plus intéressans Emilie &amp; Palémon, qui sont les
principaux Héros.</seg>
        </ab>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
